A Guide to the Sheriff Executions, 1840 - 1905
Fairfax Circuit Court Historic Records Center
Fairfax Circuit Court Historic Records Center
Guide to Sheriff Executions, 1840-1905
Fairfax Circuit Court Historic Records Center
15 linear feet.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Permanent Record of The Fairfax Circuit Court Historic Records Center.
Biographical Information
What is a court execution? A court execution is a writ of execution court order granted to put a judgement into force. A case has already gone to trial and a judgement has been granted. The court order will be carried out by a sheriff, sergeant, coroner or constable.
A judge will command a sheriff or someone of similar authority to collect the "goods and chattles" of the convicted defendant to settle the debt owed to the plaintiff. An execution will contain the following information: the names of the sheriff, plaintiff, defendant; amount of debt owed; date of when the debt originated, and the court date.
Types of executions Fieri Facias (Fi.fa.)- A writ to a sheriff for executing a judgement. Chancery - Plaintiff seeks equal distribution of assets. Writ of elegit - A judgement against a debtor's goods and chattel held by the creditor until debt is paid.
Execution Returned/Not Satisfied When an execution was not able to be served and debt unable to be satisfied; or, an execution had been served but the defendant had no property or monies to settle the debt.
Superior Court Any higher court than county court, i.e. Court of Appeals, Virginia Supreme Court, the Federal Supreme Court.
Waiver of the Homestead Act Several of the executions indicate that the defendant waived their homestead right. Below is an explanation of the Homestead Act of 1862 and what it meant to waive this right.
Homestead Act of 1862 An agreement between borrow and lender to waive the homeowner's statutory homestead rights under state law. Homestead rights protect a homeowner's equity from creditors in cases of default.
What does that mean? The Homestead Act of 1862 allowed an adult citizen to claim 160 acres of surveyed government land. They were required to "improve" the land, meaning cultivate and establish homes. After five consecutive years, the citizen would be entitled to free and clear ownership of the land. If the land was not developed within five years, then the owner waived their homestead right and was subject to the financial obligation and susceptible to collection of debt.
Scope and Content
The collection includes documents from 1840 to 1905 and is arranged chronologically, then alphabetically by surname. Along with the executions are receipts from purchases, IOUs, and bank checks to prove that the debt had either been satisfied or not satisfied.
Ledgers: The Fairfax County Historical Records also houses several ledgers that correspond with the executions. The ledgers record the names of the plaintiff, defendant, debt owed, court costs, location of the trial, what kind of warrant was executed, the return date of the warrant, counsel, warrant issue date, and outcome of the execution (whether the debt was settled, partially settled, or not satisfied.
Execution Book 1: 22 April 1870 - 1 Jan 1904
Execution Book 2: 25 November 1878 - 27 March 1907
Execution Book [3]: 4 January 1858 - 1 April 1870
Executions: 1838-1842
Execution Book: 1839-1844
Execution Book: 1842-1846
Execution Book: 1844-1855
Execution Book: 1846-1852
Execution Book: 1853-1858
Execution Book: 1855-1878/Executions Returned by Constable 1838-1848
Execution Book: 1807-1811/Executions Returned by Constable 1849-1861
Executions Returned by Constable 1866-1903
Arrangement
The sheriff executions are organized by chronological order, then alphabetized by surname of plaintiff.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
"Of Executions for Specific Property; and of Writs of Elegit and Fieri Facias" Code of Virginia 2nd Edition Including Legislation to the Year 1860. Richmond: Ritchie, Dunnavant and Co. October 19, 1860. Pages 253, 772-780.
Homestead Act (1862). Ourdocuments.gov. Accessed March 24, 2017. Homestead Act (1862)
"What is waiving homestead rights?" Reference.com. Accessed March 24, 2017. What is Waiving Homestead Rights? Article
Index Terms
Courts and Judicial; Fairfax County, Virginia; Ink, typeset, paper, parchment, pencil
Contents List
- Box 1
  - Folder 1: F - G, 1840
  - Folder 2: D-G, 1841
  - Folder 3: A-Ba, 1842
  - Folder 4: Be-Coc, 1842
  - Folder 5: Con-Ja, 1842
  - Folder 6: Ag-As, 1843
  - Folder 7: B-Bl, 1843
  - Folder 8: Bo-Cl, 1843
  - Folder 9: Co-Du, 1843
  - Folder 10: Do-Go, 1843
  - Folder 11: Gr-Ho, 1843
  - Folder 12: Hu-J, 1843
  - Folder 13: K-L, 1843
  - Folder 14: M-Mu, 1843
  - Folder 15: A-Com, 1844
  - Folder 16: Con-H, 1844
  - Folder 17: J-N, 1844
- Box 2
  - Folder 1: O-Sl, 1844
  - Folder 2: Sm-Z, 1844
  - Folder 3: A-Ch, 1845
  - Folder 4: Co-D, 1845
  - Folder 5: E-G, 1845
  - Folder 6: H-K, 1845
  - Folder 8: O-Sh, 1845
  - Folder 9: Si-W, 1845
  - Folder 10: A-Col, 1846
  - Folder 11: Com-Fa, 1846
  - Folder 12: Fi-Ha, 1846
  - Folder 13: He-L, 1846
  - Folder 14: M-P, 1846
- Box 3
  - Folder 2: V-W, 1846
  - Folder 3: A-B, 1847
  - Folder 4: C-Fe, 1847
  - Folder 5: Fi-Ho, 1847
  - Folder 6: Hu-Mil, 1847
  - Folder 7: Mil-R, 1847
  - Folder 8: S-W, 1847
  - Folder 9: Miscellaneous, 1847
  - Folder 10: A-C, 1848
  - Folder 11: D-G, 1848
  - Folder 12: H-J, 1848
  - Folder 13: K-M, 1848
  - Folder 14: N-S, 1848
  - Folder 15: T-Y, 1848
  - Folder 16: A-W, 1848 Superior Court
- Box 4
  - Folder 1: A-C, 1849
  - Folder 2: D-H, 1849
  - Folder 3: J-R, 1849
  - Folder 4: S-W, 1849
  - Folder 5: A-Gr, 1850
  - Folder 6: Gu-M, 1850
  - Folder 7: N-Y, 1850
  - Folder 8: A-W, 1851
  - Folder 9: A-F, 1852
- Box 5
  - Folder 1: A-O, 1853; Constable's execution not satisfied
  - Folder 2: P-W, 1853; Constable's execution not satisfied
  - Folder 3: A-W, 1854
  - Folder 4: B-W, 1854; Constable's execution not satisfied
  - Folder 5: A-C, 1855
  - Folder 6: D-H, 1855
  - Folder 7: J-O, 1855
  - Folder 8: P-W, 1855
  - Folder 9: A-W, 1856; Constable's execution not satisfied
  - Folder 10: A-C, 1856
  - Folder 11: D-He, 1856
  - Folder 12: H-P, 1856
- Box 6
  - Folder 1: R-W, 1856
  - Folder 2: A-C, 1857
  - Folder 3: D-G, 1857
  - Folder 4: H-K, 1857
  - Folder 5: L-R, 1857
  - Folder 6: S-W, 1857
  - Folder 7: A-D, 1857; Constable's execution not satisfied
  - Folder 8: E-L, 1857; Constable's execution not satisfied
  - Folder 9: M-R 1857; Constable's execution not satisfied
  - Folder 10: S-W 1857; Constable's execution not satisfied
  - Folder 11: A-C 1858
  - Folder 12: D-G 1858
  - Folder 13: H-M 1858
  - Folder 14: N-S 1858
  - Folder 15: T-W 1858
  - Folder 16: A-C 1859
  - Folder 17: D-G 1859
  - Folder 18: H-J 1859
- Box 7
  - Folder 1: K-N, 1859
  - Folder 2: O-S, 1859
  - Folder 3: T-Y, 1859
  - Folder 4: A-B, 1858; Execution Returned/Not Satisfied
  - Folder 5: Ca-Co, 1858; Execution Returned/Not Satisfied
  - Folder 6: Co-E, 1858; Execution Returned/Not Satisfied
  - Folder 7: F-Ga, 1858; Execution Returned/Not Satisfied
  - Folder 8: G, 1858; Execution Returned/Not Satisfied
  - Folder 9: H-Le, 1858; Execution Returned/Not Satisfied
  - Folder 10: Lo-O, 1858; Execution Returned/Not Satisfied
  - Folder 11: P-Ro, 1858; Execution Returned/Not Satisfied
  - Folder 12: Ru-T, 1858; Execution Returned/Not Satisfied
  - Folder 13: W-V, 1858; Execution Returned/Not Satisfied
  - Folder 14: A-C, 1859; Execution Returned/Not Satisfied
  - Folder 15: D-G, 1859; Execution Returned/Not Satisfied
  - Folder 16: H-J, 1859; Execution Returned/Not Satisfied
  - Folder 17: K-P, 1859; Execution Returned/Not Satisfied
  - Folder 18: R-W, 1859; Execution Returned/Not Satisfied
  - Folder 19: A-B, 1860; Execution Returned/Not Satisfied
  - Folder 20: C-E, 1860; Execution Returned/Not Satisfied
  - Folder 21: F-Hi, 1860; Execution Returned/Not Satisfied
  - Folder 22: H-M, 1860; Execution Returned/Not Satisfied
  - Folder 23: W-V, 1860; Execution Returned/Not Satisfied
  - Folder 24: A-D, 1861; Execution Returned/Not Satisfied
  - Folder 25: E-L, 1861; Execution Returned/Not Satisfied
  - Folder 26: M-R, 1861; Execution Returned/Not Satisfied
- Box 8
  - Folder 1: J-O, 1860; Execution Returned/Not Satisfied
  - Folder 2: P-Y, 1860; Execution Returned/Not Satisfied
  - Folder 3: G-W, 1860; Chancery Execution
  - Folder 4: A-B, 1860
  - Folder 5: C-F, 1860
  - Folder 6: G-H, 1860
  - Folder 7: J-K, 1860
  - Folder 8: M-P, 1860
  - Folder 10: A-D, 1861
  - Folder 11: E-Herbert, 1861
  - Folder 12: Hickey-Perkens, 1861
  - Folder 13: Powell-W, 1861
  - Folder 14: 1864
  - Folder 15: A-M, 1865
  - Folder 16: P-W, 1865
  - Folder 17: A-F, 1866
  - Folder 18: F-V, 1866
  - Folder 19: W, 1866
  - Folder 20: A-Commonwealth, 1867
  - Folder 21: Commonwealth - Ganton, 1867
  - Folder 22: Glassock-House, 1867
- Box 9
  - Folder 1: Jackson-L, 1867
  - Folder 2: M-R, 1867
  - Folder 3: S-V, 1867
  - Folder 4: W, 1867
  - Folder 5: A-Coleman, 1868
  - Folder 6: Commonwealth - E, 1868
  - Folder 7: F-Jackson, 1868
  - Folder 8: Jackson's Admin-McCawley, 1868
  - Folder 9: Moore-S, 1868
  - Folder 10: T-W, 1868
  - Folder 11: C-W, 1868; Execution not satisfied
  - Folder 12: A-E, 1869
  - Folder 13: F-H, 1869
  - Folder 14: J-P, 1869
  - Folder 15: R-S, 1869
  - Folder 16: T-W, 1869
  - Folder 17: A-J; Executions not Satisfied
  - Folder 18: P-W; Executions not Satisfied
- Box 10
  - Folder 1: A-C, 1870
  - Folder 2: D-F, 1870
  - Folder 3: G-H, 1870
  - Folder 4: J-M, 1870
  - Folder 5: O-S, 1870
  - Folder 6: T-W, 1870
  - Folder 7: B-W, 1870; Executions not Satisfied
  - Folder 8: A-H, 1871
  - Folder 9: J-P, 1871
  - Folder 10: R-T, 1871
  - Folder 11: U-W, 1871
  - Folder 12: A-W, 1871; Executions not Satisfied
  - Folder 13: A-E, 1872
  - Folder 14: G-K, 1872
  - Folder 15: L-S, 1872
  - Folder 16: T-W, 1872
  - Folder 17: A-W, 1872; Executions not Satisfied
  - Folder 18: A-W, 1873
  - Folder 19: D-W, 1873; Executions not Satisfied
  - Folder 20: A-F, 1874
  - Folder 21: G-S, 1874
  - Folder 22: T-W, 1874
  - Folder 23: A-W, 1874; Executions not Satisfied
  - Folder 24: A-F, 1875
  - Folder 25: G-M, 1875
  - Folder 26: O-W, 1875
  - Folder 27: A-W, 1875; Executions not Satisfied
  - Folder 28: A-G, 1876
- Box 11
  - Folder 1: H-L, 1876
  - Folder 2: M-W, 1876
  - Folder 3: A-W, 1876; Executions not Satisfied
  - Folder 4: A-G, 1877
  - Folder 5: H-P, 1877
  - Folder 6: R-W, 1877
  - Folder 7: A-W, 1877; Executions not Satisfied
  - Folder 8: B-G, 1878
  - Folder 9: H-P, 1878
  - Folder 10: R-W, 1878
  - Folder 11: B-W, 1878; Executions not Satisfied
  - Folder 12: A-Horner, 1879
  - Folder 13: Hunt-R, 1879
  - Folder 14: S-Y, 1879
  - Folder 15: A-T, 1879; Executions not Satisfied
  - Folder 16: A-H, 1880
  - Folder 17: I-Z, 1880
  - Folder 18: A-D, 1881
  - Folder 19: E-R, 1881
  - Folder 20: S-Z, 1881
  - Folder 21: A-H, 1882
- Box 12
  - Folder 1: I-Z, 1882
  - Folder 2: A-H, 1883
  - Folder 3: I-Q, 1883
  - Folder 4: R-Z, 1883
  - Folder 5: A-H, 1884
  - Folder 6: I-R, 1884
  - Folder 7: S-Z, 1884
  - Folder 8: A-G, 1885
  - Folder 9: H-Z, 1885
  - Folder 10: A-J, 1886
  - Folder 11: K-Z, 1886
  - Folder 12: A-D, 1887
  - Folder 13: E-L, 1887
  - Folder 14: M-Z, 1887
  - Folder 15: A-D, 1888
  - Folder 16: E-L, 1888
- Box 13
  - Folder 1: M-R, 1888
  - Folder 2: S-Z, 1888
  - Folder 3: A-C, 1889
  - Folder 4: D-J, 1889
  - Folder 5: K-P, 1889
  - Folder 6: R-T, 1889
  - Folder 7: U-W, 1889
  - Folder 8: A-G, 1890
  - Folder 9: H-P, 1890
  - Folder 10: R-Z, 1890
  - Folder 11: A-J, 1891
  - Folder 12: K-Z, 1891
  - Folder 13: A-F, 1892
  - Folder 14: G-O, 1892
  - Folder 15: P-Z, 1892
  - Folder 16: A-E, 1893
  - Folder 17: G-N, 1893
  - Folder 18: O-Z, 1893
  - Folder 19: A-E, 1894
  - Folder 20: O-W, 1894
- Box 14
  - Folder 1: F-M, 1894
  - Folder 2: A-D, 1895
  - Folder 3: E-H, 1895
  - Folder 4: J-M, 1895
  - Folder 5: N-S, 1895
  - Folder 6: T-W, 1895
  - Folder 7: A-D, 1896
  - Folder 8: E-H, 1896
  - Folder 9: J-N, 1896
  - Folder 10: O-S, 1896
  - Folder 11: T-Z, 1896
  - Folder 12: A-D, 1897
  - Folder 13: D-J, 1897
  - Folder 14: K-O, 1897
  - Folder 15: P-U, 1897
  - Folder 16: A-D, 1898
  - Folder 17: E-J, 1898
- Box 15
  - Folder 1: K-P, 1898
  - Folder 2: R-Z, 1898
  - Folder 3: A-G, 1899
  - Folder 4: H-P, 1899
  - Folder 5: R-Z, 1899
  - Folder 6: A-F, 1900
  - Folder 7: G-M, 1900
  - Folder 8: O-Z, 1900
  - Folder 9: A-E, 1901
  - Folder 10: F-L, 1901
  - Folder 11: M-R, 1901
  - Folder 12: S-Z, 1901
  - Folder 13: A-I, 1902
  - Folder 14: J-Q, 1902
  - Folder 15: R-Z, 1902
  - Folder 16: A-K, 1903
  - Folder 17: M-Z, 1903
  - Folder 18: A-Z, 1904
  - Folder 19: R, 1905